A Guide to the George Zeidenstein papers FA263
Rockefeller Archive Center
George Zeidenstein papers
1976-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Zeidenstein, George
Population Council
FA263
9.12 Cubic Feet
24 manuscript boxes, consisting of fifty-eight volumes of correspondence and one volume of personal travel notes.
Related Materials
Population Council records; JDR 3rd Papers: Population Interests (Series 1, Subseries 5; and Series 3, Subseries 4)
Biographical / Historical
George Zeidenstein, born July 29th 1929, started his undergraduate education at the University of Pittsburgh in 1947 and transferred to the University of Michigan-Ann Arbor in 1948. Zeidenstein later attended and graduated from Harvard Law School.
Zeidenstein began his professional career as a corporate and securities lawyer on Wall Street. However, after ten years he left Wall Street to work in support of voter registration drives for African-Americans in Mississippi and Arkansas in the 1960s. Emboldened by this experience, he then took on the directorship of the Peace Corps in Nepal, where he served from 1965 to 1968.
Continuing his work in international development issues, from 1971-1976, Zeidenstein served as the first Ford Foundation Representative in newly independent Bangladesh.
In 1976, John D. Rockefeller, 3rd the founder and first president of the Population Council, recruited Zeidenstein as the fifth president of the Council. Zeidenstein served as president of the Population Council for seventeen years. His presidency was quite innovative and transformative for the Council, particularly in the areas of diversity, equity and inclusion. Zeidenstein sought to internationalize the Council's board, staff, it's collaborative arrangements, and actively worked to expand its donor base. He added regional representatives to the Council's organizational chart and sought to decentralize decisionmaking by delegating authority to senior staff within the countries that the Council was active. Most importantly, Zeidenstein vastly expanded the status and role of women within the Council, and programatically established the role of women and girls and those communities and populations the Council served as a central theme of all Council activities. In 1993, Zeidenstein became a Distinguished Fellow at Harvard University's Center for Population and Development Studies.
For his work, Zeidenstein has been decorated by the governments of Senegal and Finland. Zeidenstein also served as a Board Member of the International Center for Research on Women.
In 2001 George Zeidenstein's memoirs, Lifelines, was published by Modern Memoirs Publishing of Amherst, MA. He passed away August 21, 2021 aged 92 in Goshen, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of George Zeidenstein's professional correspondence, spanning his seventeen years of service to the Population Council. Records include internal Population Council memoranda and reports, as well as travel notes and drafts of speeches for public appearances.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as one series, and predominantly remains in its original chronological order, as maintained by George Zeidenstein.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The George Zeidenstein papers were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by George Zeidenstein in 2010.
- Professional correspondence, 1976-1992; 1
  - 1976 January-August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1976 September-December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1977 January-March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1977 March-May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1977 May-August (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1977 August-December (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1978 January-April (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1978 May-August (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1978 September-December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1979 January-August (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1979 August-December (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1980 January-September (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1980 September-December (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1981 January-April (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - 1981 May-July (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - 1981 August-October (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - 1981 November-December (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - 1982 January-March (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - 1982 March-May (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - 1982 June-August (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - 1982 September-December (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - 1983 January-February (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - 1983 March-June (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - 1983 July-September (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - 1983 October-December (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - 1984 January-February (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - 1984 March-April (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - 1984 May-August (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - 1984 September-December (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - 1985 January-February (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - 1985 March-June (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - 1985 July-September (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - 1985 October-December (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - 1985 January-March (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - 1986 April-June (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - 1986 July-August (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - 1986 September-December (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - 1987 January-April (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - 1987 May-September (Box 16, Folder 39)
  - 1987 October-December (Box 16, Folder 40)
  - 1988 January-March (Box 17, Folder 41)
  - 1988 April-June (Box 17, Folder 42)
  - 1988 July-September (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - 1988 October-December (Box 18, Folder 44)
  - 1989 January-July (Box 18, Folder 45)
  - 1989 August-October (Box 19, Folder 46)
  - 1989 November-December (Box 19, Folder 47)
  - 1990 January-March (Box 19, Folder 48)
  - 1990 April-September (Box 20, Folder 49)
  - 1990 October-December (Box 20, Folder 50)
  - 1991 January-March (Box 21, Folder 51)
  - 1991 April-June (Box 21, Folder 52)
  - 1991 July-September (Box 21, Folder 53)
  - 1991 October-December (Box 22, Folder 54)
  - 1992 January-March (Box 22, Folder 55)
  - 1992 April-June (Box 23, Folder 56)
  - 1992 July-September (Box 23, Folder 57)
  - 1992 October-December (Box 24, Folder 58)
  - Travel Notes, 1979-1982 (Box 24, Folder 59)
  - Statement-Global Committee of Parliamentarians on Population & Development, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 60)